Guide to the Centennial Oral History Project Oral Histories 1982-1988
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Centennial Oral History Project Oral Histories
1982-1988
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 202
Washington State University.
11 Linear feet of shelf space 22 Boxes
Interviews and records from Washington State University Centennial Oral History Project.
The Washington State University Centennial Oral History Project (COHP) was formally established with a $5,000 grant from the WSU Foundation in 1983. From this beginning, COHP coordinator Linda Lilles initiated a network of volunteer interviewers and interviewees from the various facets of the University community, including alumni, retirees, faculty, staff, and administration of long standing. Since the initial grant, the Office of Centennial Planning and the History Department have funded the COHP, with the bulk of the program under the leadership of Keith Williams. Coordinator from August, 1983 to November, 1987, Williams built up the collection to include 150 interviews with as many as 80 volunteers.
The COHP operates under a "unit history" format whereby each university department or unit has been asked to participate so that a balanced collective history emerges. Forty-five departments/units are represented in the collection. An important emphasis of COHP in addition to departmental/unit histories has been the 25 Golden Grad interviews, undertaken from 1984 to 1987, during the 50th anniversary alumni celebrations held each spring. By the end of the Centennial Oral History Project in June, 1988, 174 interviews have been processed and transcribed. This is a significant feat, as the Oral History Office has no interviewing staff and relies soley upon volunteers to conduct the interviews. The resulting interviews have been made available to Centennial historians and any others who wish to research or just reminisce.
Each interview in the first series has been transcribed, but due to budget constraints, most of them have not been edited. If in doubt on a name or years, consult Campus Directories or Catalogs in Holland Library. Also, remember that these interviews are informal conversations where errors in grammar sometimes occur. The description outlines basic information--the interviewer, interviewee, number of tapes, interview date, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC) location, any additional material filed with the originals, and a brief sketch of topics discussed during the interview.
An index to departments and subjects exists in print form at WSU Libraries: Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections. In addition to information presented here, the print index also contains a subject index and a university department index.
During digitization of these in 2013, it was realized that a 1970 History of WSU's Physics Program roundtable was included in the Golden Grads cassettes in box 21; its provenance is unknown but it is speculated that it might have come as supporting material to Dr. Band's interview (Box 1).
This collection is divided into three series. The main series (Box 1-20) consists of one-on-one interviews. The second series lists the Golden Grad interviews- group interviews with returning alumni (Box 21). The final series (Box 22) contains all relevant paperwork.
The majority of the audio recordings from this collection have been digitized and can be found online in the WSU Oral Histories Project Digital Collection.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection is a compilation of the accessions: UA 84-33, UA 84-37, UA 85-05, UA 85-08, UA 85-12, UA 85-16, UA 85-27, UA 85-28, UA 85-45, UA 86-02, UA 87-17, UA 87-30.
An interview, with James Elder, was discovered in another collection in 2011 and moved to this one.
One additional Centennial Oral History was completed too late to be included, and is now held separately as the Centennial Oral History Interview with Charles Byron "CB" Jones, 1990 October 31 (CT 23)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Lilles, Linda.
Washington State University -- Records and correspondence.; Washington State University -- History.
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State); Oral Histories
- Series 1: One-on-one Interviews
  - Ackley, William B. Horticulture - Chair, March 15, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 3 tapes (Box 1)
    Development of landscape architecture program at WSU. Washington state's wine grape industry. Horticulture Department's relationship with neighboring states and provinces. Horticulture department at Johnson Hall. Cooperation with USDA. Responsibilities as chairman. Research stations. Changes in the department over the years. Foreign work and cooperation. Extension programs.
    Photograph of Ackley, 1985. Resume. Ackley's Recollections and 5 pages of notes used for the interview.
  - Adams, Janet Alumni - Education, 1976, July 16, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 1)
    Family members who are WSU graduates. Personal background. Student experiences at WSU - work, studies, activities, classes, professors, equipment, and facilities. Campus and social life in the early 1970s. Comments on research and teaching assistants. Campus health care. Religious activities of the early 1970s.
    Family tree.
  - Adams, Mark F. Division of Industrial Research, September 5, 1986; Schnaitter, Allene; 2 tapes (Box 1)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC, 1938-51. Professional career at WSU, 1942-74. Personal research at WSU. Shift in research and teaching duties. Relationship between the Division of Industrial Research and the College of Engineering. Administration of, and attitude toward Division of Industrial Research. Early days in Pullman. Materials donated to WSU archives. Personal interests.
  - Adams, Ruth Alumni - Music/Education, 1941. Faculty Wife - Mark F. Adams, Division of Industrial Research, September 5, 1986; Schnaitter, Allene; 1 tapes (Box 1)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC, 1936-41. Early years in Pullman. Impressions of WSC. Marriage to Mark F. Adams, Professor of Chemistry. Founding of Montessori School in Pullman, 1969. Montessori theory of education. Activities with faculty wives. Mark F. Adam's consulting work. Personal interests.
  - Anderson, Gilmore Engineering - Foundry and Wood Products Lab, June 9, 1987; Backus, Janice; 3 tapes (Box 1)
    Personal background. Work at WSU Foundry, 1943-1950 - facilities, supervisors, work with light alloy metals, and crew. Employment with foundry at the Division of Industrial Research. Extensive discussion on various projects the foundry undertook. Work with Hydraulics Department. Work on developing hop dryer. Closure of foundry. Employment with Wood Products Lab - crew, supervisors, graduate students, facilities, salaries and promotions, and departmental social activities. Extensive discussion on Wood Products Lab's projects. Chairs of Engineering. Physical development of campus.
  - Backus, Donald Alumni - Agricultural Engineering, 1952, June 3, 1987; Backus, Janice; 2 tapes (Box 1)
    Personal background. Pine Manor, a male residence hall - social events, house mother, fellow hallmates. Student life and favorite instructors. A typical day.
    Photocopy page of Pine Manor residents, including Backus.
  - Bailey, Roy and Wanda Animal Science - Farm Manager, February 20, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 1 tapes (Box 1)
    Personal background. Roy's career, 1924-72 (manager of Farm Services, 1944-72). Locations of various buildings on campus. Bailey's work with Clydesdale horses and blacksmithing. Locations of plots of farm land near campus. Colleagues over the years.
    Paper entitled "Recollections of WSU" by Roy Bailey. Copies of photos about cutting wheat, Clydesdales, sunflowers, and Bailey's retirement party. Photos of Roy and Wanda Bailey, and photo of Roy with Rod Bertramson.
  - Band, William Physics - Chair, April 25, 1985; Park, James L. and George E. Duvall; 1 tapes (Box 1)
    Recollections of Physics department since 1949. Band's chairmanship, 1958-67. WSU administration. Importance of teaching.
    Autobiography and a March, 1967 WSU Invited Address entitled "Shocks in Physics and in Society." Paper by Alfred B. Butler, Physics, entitled "Some History of the WSU Physics Department."
  - Bartuska, Tom J. Architecture, November 26, 1985; Graham, Channell; 1 tapes (Box 2)
    Personal background. Undergraduate and graduate career at the University of Illinois. Travelling scholarship to Europe, 1958 - worked at a United Nations Association work camp in Austria building houses for refugees. WSU career, 1963 to present. Architecture department - size, faculty, courses, and facilities. Cooperative program. Outstanding students. 1970 Fulbright and sabbatical to Afghanistan and its positive affect on his career.
    Resume
  - Bearse, Gordon Animal Science - Poultry Science, Puyallup Experiment Station, May 1, 1984; Rasmussen, Lowell W.; 2 tapes (Box 2)
    Biography of Bearse. Professional career at WSU, 1929-72. Poultry industry problems and research programs. Colleagues and their work. Communication of research findings to industry groups, producers, and other researchers. Personal service to scientific community and local area.
    Biographical sketch. News release from WWREC about Bearse's retirement.
  - Bement, Kenyon T. Alumni - Business Administration, 1934, May 14, 1987; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 2)
    Student days at WSC -fraternities, teachers, "Yell King" activities, student attitudes, and classmates.
  - Bennett, Edward M. (#1) History, October 30, 1985; Hadlow, Robert; 2 tapes (Box 2)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1961-present. History department - students, courses, faculty, and facilities. Focus of departmental change, 1961-85. Praise for WSU's graduate program. Social atmosphere of Pullman. Personal hobbies. Private and professional associations and activities. Athletics at WSU. Student protests of the late 1960s and early 1970s. Administrative response to students. Violence on WSU campus. Mascots and student identity. Salary inequities. Performance of three WSU administrations.
    Curriculum vita.
  - Bennett, Edward M. (#2) History, July 22, 1986; Hall, David; 2 tapes (Box 2)
    Professional career at WSU, 1961-present. History department - courses, work load, research, faculty, character of department, and students. Experience as Faculty Athletic Representative to the Pacific 10 Athletic Conference. Importance of athletics in generating alumni financial support and identification. Why Bennett came to WSU and reasons for staying.
  - Benzel, Brian Alumni - Business Administration, 1970, February 8, 1988; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 2)
    Student days at WSU - student politics, student attitudes, and experiences as Associated Students of Washington State University (ASWSU) President.
  - Bertramson, B. Rodney Agronomy and Soils - Chair, December 30, 1985; Ehlers, Melvin R.; 3 tapes (Box 2)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1949-85. Highlights in Agronomy program. Agronomy Department - faculty, cooperation with other departments, extension, and chairs. Arrival at WSU and living in Pullman. Relationships with state and regional associations and USDA. Professional societies. Tenure as department chairman. Philosophy on departmental administration. Mission of a land-grant university. Professionalism. Program for observing teaching. Land and facilities supervision. Teaching loads. Tribute to Ag. teachers. Turbulent times of the late 1960s and early 1970s.
    6 articles by Bertramson. Bibliography on professional agronomists. Four photos of Bertramson - 1945,1952,1970, and 1984.
  - Betts, Attie L. Electrical Engineering, April 21, 1985; Knox, R. F.; 1 tapes (Box 2)
    Personal background. World War II. WSU career, 1955-1978. Growth of Engineering Department and faculty. Development of honors and PhD programs. Academic cooperation with other Pacific Northwest electrical engineering departments. Colleagues. Outstanding students. WSU administration under President C. C. French.
  - Bhatia, Vishnu N. Office of International Education and Honors Program - Director. Pharmacy, March 26, 1986; Slind, Marvin; 1 tapes (Box 2)
    Early years of International Programs Office. Establishment of study abroad and exchange programs. Directors of International Programs. Professional career at WSU, 1952-present. Changes in personnel and focus of International Programs. Administration's support. Creation of International Programs Development Office. Bhatia's guidelines for establishing study abroad programs. Rewarding aspects of experience with International Programs. Creation of Language Center.
    Biographical data.
  - Bobb, Bernard History, July 11, 1986; Hall, David; 1 tapes (Box 2)
    Professional career at WSU, 1949-1980. Early years of the Political Science and History department - course load, extension programs, research interests, and split of the department. Publications and dissertation background. Colleagues. Impressions of chairmen and WSU presidents. Effects of McCarthy era on department and campus. Campus unrest of the 1960s and 1970s. Effect of Chicano Studies on Mexican history. Changes from Resident Instructional Staff to Senate. Financial conditions and status of department and faculty. Pullman. History department (academic quality, publication standards, pay, Latin American historians, and grad students). Retirement. Current Latin American events. Lack of objectivity in history.
  - Bonn, Art and Marge Alumni - Entomology, 1925 (A.B.); English, 1924 (M.B.), December 12, 1986; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 3)
    Student days at WSU - teachers, fraternities and sororities, social activities, library, classmates, fashions, and campus grounds.
  - Boyington, Alfred Music, April 27, 1983; Spicer, Randall; 2 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. How Boyington came to WSU. Career, 1933-1973. WWII, and graduate school at the University of Michigan. Colleagues. Agony Hall (old music building). Music facilities. Performing days and undergraduate years at Julliard. Outstanding students. "Tall Indians" organization at WSU.
  - Brain, George Education - Dean, May 10, 1983; Grunewald, Marjorie; 1 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1965-1983. Establishment of the the Department of Education, 1964. Evolution of Home Economics and Agricultural Education. Basic Education Act. Contributions of WSU's Education department to the state. Distribution of Education graduates from Washington universities and colleges. New thrusts: industrial technology, and expanding international market in education. Impressions of being a Dean.
    Memorandum from Dean Zeno Katterle indicating merger of the two Physical Education departments with the College of Education and the establishment of the Department of Education. Newspaper article on Brain's resignation from Education Deanship.
  - Breakey, Nettie C. (Esselbaugh) Food Sciences and Human Nutrition, April 4, 1988; Hard, Margaret; 1 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. Professional WSU career, 1946-1956. Nutrition classes, graduate students, and curriculum in related sciences. Impressions of the Palouse country. College of Home Economics - faculty, research facilities, and research. Social activities. Professional salaries. Travel. Relationship with Home Economics Extension staff.
    Copy from "Who's Who of American Women" & "American Men of Science." List of professional publications. 2 reprints co-authored by Breakey: "Nutritional Status of -Ten Family Groups in WA. St.," & "Effect of Nutritional Education on Food Habits."
  - Bucklin, Robert Alumni - 1925, December 12, 1986; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 3)
    Reminiscences of Bucklin's father, Robert Eden Bucklin, a WSC alumnus. Impressions of WSU Presidents.
  - Bundy, Murray W. English - Chair, June 16, 1984; Elder, James H.; 2 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1928-56. Phi Beta Kappa honor society. Extensive discussion on President and Mrs. Compton and the Compton administration. Beaver Creek Camp Association. Responsibilities of department chairman. Early days of the English department.
  - Bushaw, Donald Mathematics, May 14, 1986; DeTemple, Duane; 2 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. Campus and math department as an undergraduate, 1943-1949. Campus changes over the years. Influential professors. Graduate experience at Princeton. Professional career at WSU, 1952-present. Math department in the 1950s - colleagues, curriculum, etc. Students over the years. Pure and applied mathematics. Changes in teaching math, and new directions. Professional organizations and research interests. Comparisons of various administrations/administrators. Affiliated departments - astronomy and computer science. Doctor of Arts program.
  - Buss, Irven 0. Zoology, September 18, 1985; Jonas, Robert J.; 1 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1948-73. Early years of Wildlife Biology. Personal research (elephants). Wildlife Biology program - graduate students, faculty, and zoology chairs. WSU's administration in relation to Wildlife Biology. Principles of Wildlife Conservation class.
    Paper on history of Wildlife Biology program by Buss entitled, "Status, Needs, and a Proposed Program for Wildlife Biology at Washington State University." No date.
  - Calbick, Chester J. Physics, January 27, 1985; Donaldson, E.E.; 1 tapes (Box 3)
    Student career at WSU, 1921-25. Work at Bell Labs, 1925-68, including electron diffraction, electron microscopes, Calbick-Davisson formula, early television, et cetera. Senior research physicist with WSU after retirement from Bell Labs, 1973-present.
  - Caraher, Joe Alumni Association, July 5, 1983; Caraher, Pat; 2 tapes (Box 3)
    Personal background. Establishment of alumni clubs in and out of Washington. Alumni meetings and gathering support. Changes in responsibilities of Alumni Association (AA). AA's relationship with the President and Board of Regents. Principles in early AA and Cougar Club. Alumni leadership scholarship program and alumni achievement award. Student involvement in AA. Caraher's feelings of establishing an alumni house on campus. Golden Grad reunions. New directions Caraher believes AA should take.
  - Chisolm, Florence and Marshall Alumni - Mathematics, 1927 (F.C); 1928 (M.C.), January 17, 1987; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 3)
    Student days at WSC - professors, Greek versus dormitory living, clothing fashions, social activities, and classmates.
  - Coleman, Dorothea Physical Education, September 9, 1983; Washburn, Joanne; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    WSU career, 1948-1974. Supporter of women's unlimited dribble basketball. Eligibility of women in athletics. Restrictions in athletics. Involvement with volleyball. Officiating. Physical Education department - colleagues, courses, and students. Personal background. Concerns for teaching competency - teacher education standards in Physical Education program. Committee work on maintaining attendence requirement in P.E. courses. Contributions to P.E. department. Committee service. Sexism and maintaining University standards.
    TAPE 1 IS MISSING
  - Cook, Dorothy Education, June 15, 1983; Grunewald, Marjorie B.; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1949-1973. Philosophy of education. Computers. Attraction of, and life at WSU. Fine Arts and Education departments. Sabbatical in Mexico. Artistic goals for children. The "Art Shop." Pullman schools. Workshops and extension classes. WSU's changing curriculum. Inspirational teachers. WWII years.
  - Coonrad, Dan Animal Science, February 12, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. Animal Science student, 1958-63. Career with WSU Animal Science Department, 1967-present. History and uses of the Old Beef Barn. Colleagues. Discussion of manure lagoons, and silage and hay making. Future of the beef industry. Cross breeding of cattle.
    Copies of photographs about rope halter tying class, 1959; Coonrad with grand champion bull, 1960. 2 photos of Coonrad at Old Beef Barn, 1985.
  - Cosgriffe, Harry Adult and Continuing Education, May 30, 1985; Long, James; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. Masters of Adult and Continuing Education Program (MACE) - adult learning course, program planning course. Transition from Masters of Extension Program to MACE program. Development of a regional association of adult educators (Northwest Adult Education Association). Future of adult education.Reflections on career at WSU as extension administrator, professor in the MACE, and as international developer.
  - Cossalman, Gertrude Education - Administrative Assistant, February 3, 1984; Grunewald, Marjorie; 2 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1942-1976. Early years of the Education department. Professors. College Hall. History of teacher certification. Job description and evolution of duties up to Administrative Assistant. Recollections of and relations with students. Establishment of the department and Cleveland Hall. Colleagues. Relations with the rest of the university. Support services for the faculty. Problems with the program. State Office of Education. Dean/chairman split of authority. Student teaching program. Teacher quality.
  - Crawford, William Education, March 23, 1982; Grunewald, Marjorie; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1954-72. Junior colleges and their separation from public schools. Early years of the Education department. Influence of Education department on Washington's community colleges. Current issues in education, especially in community colleges. Comparison of junior colleges and universities. Crawford's retirement.
    Obituaries from local papers, March 26, 1983.
  - Deeter, Isaac (Ike) Physical Education - Alumni, 1928. Boxing Coach, June 23, 1984; Tidrick, K.A. (Andy); 2 tapes (Box 4)
    Personal background. Student experiences - Sigma Nu fraternity, social events, and athletics. Boxing experiences - Golden Gloves. Job at Potlatch, 1929. WSU professional career as boxing coach, 1931-1967. Amateur and college leagues, notable boxers, and memorable bouts. Navy Pre-flight program during WWII. Demise of boxing program. Intramural and instructional boxing. Colleagues and anecdotes. Family. WSU administrations. Student athletes. Retirement activities.
  - Deutsch, Lenna Baird Bacteriology - Alumni, 1926. Instructor. Faculty Wife - Herman Deutsch, History, June 6, 1984; Nakata, Herb; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    Circumstances bringing Deutsch to WSC. Student years at WSC, 1922-1926. Anecdote on diptheria scare. Graduate student experiences, 1928-1929. Experiences as an instructor, 1929. Relationship between Bacteriology professor, Dr. Victor Burke and History professor, Dr. Deutsch. Marriage to Dr. Herman Deutsch, 1930. Bacteriology department - facilities, students, faculty. Presentation of Sigma Alpha Omicron pin to H.M. Nakata. Social life and codes on WSC campus.
  - Dils, Eugene W. Dean of Students, Alumni, May 12, 1987; Fry, Richard B.; 1 tapes (Box 4)
    Dils' student days at WSC in the (?)1930s - organizations (Theta Nu Epsilon, TNE), social rules, teachers, clothing fashions, classmates, and student politics.Noel: Reminiscences of Buck Bailey and WSU baseball. Norman: Perceptions of college athletics today.
    Tape and transcript also contains short interviews with WSU alumni, Bob Noel and Stanley Norman.
  - Dingle, Richard W. Forestry and Range Management, April 15, 1986; Harris, Grant; 2 tapes (Box 4)